Guide to the Tony Martin Papers 1960-2006 MSS 190
© 2009 Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series I: Documentary and Graphic Material
  - Subseries C: Interactive Sculptures
    Consists mostly of announcements and photographs pertaining to Tony Martin's interactive sculptures. Abundant sketches and notes (including schematics) relating to material in Subseries C may be found in Subseries D, under "Interactive Sculptures," "New Media Works…" and the individual names of the installations.
    - Interaction Room (or Game Room) (20 x 20 x 10 room containing light and projection installation activated by viewers using game principles) - Howard Wise Gallery, New York, NY ***see also*** Oversize, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Column - Howard Wise Gallery, New York, NY, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Door - Howard Wise Gallery, New York, NY, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 78)
      General note
      "Door" is in the permanent collection of the Butler Institute of American Art, Youngstown, OH
    - The Well - Everson Museum, permanent collection, Syracuse, NY, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 79)
      "The Well" is in the permanent collection of the Everson Museum, Syracuse, NY
    - You, Me, We - Howard Wise Gallery, New York, NY, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Word Wall - Longridge Plaza, permanent collection, Rochester, NY, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Subseries D: Sketches, Notes & Miscellaneous
    Contains rich material relating to Subseries C: Interactive Sculptures, including handwritten notes, sketches and schematics of electronic circuits. Other material includes contact sheets as well as press clippings pertaining to Tony Martin's works. Subseries D is arranged alphabetically.
    - Address book / Appointment book / Notebook, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Biography & Chronology of New Media Works, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Circuitry (with Pauline Oliveros), 1967+2004, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Door - Sketches and schematics of electronic circuits, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Interactive Sculptures, including "Column" and "The Well", 1968 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - New Media Works including "Climate Sculpture," "Nodes," and "Xytopy", 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Photograph of Tony Martin, Sal Martirano, William Wegman, ca. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Press - miscellaneous, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Schematics of electronic circuits for Carl Countryman, Game Room, E.A.T., 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Score Drawings - "storyboard-composition", ca. 1970s (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Sequences, ca. 1970s (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Sketches, Drawings for Pieces ***see also*** Oversize, ca. 1970s (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Theater Sculpture For Watchers, Walkers, Touchers (a 140 foot long interactive polysensory course in an octagonal room) - San Francisco Museum of Art, CA, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Word Wall - Longridge Plaza, permanent collection, Rochester, NY, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Subseries E: Correspondence
    Consists mainly of Tony Martin's letter and e-mail correspondence with notable artists and art organizations. Subseries E is arranged alphabetically by two main groups, individuals and institutions.
    - Individuals - Ashton, Dore, 1992-1998 (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Individuals - Bermant, David W., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - Individuals - Bly, Carol, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Individuals - Bly, Robert (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - Individuals - Caws, Mary Ann, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 100)
    - Individuals - Chadabe, Joel, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 101)
    - Individuals - Conte, Richard, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 102)
    - Individuals - Dowling, Jack (Box 1, Folder 103)
    - Individuals - Friedman, Martin, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 104)
    - Individuals - Gerz, Jochen, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 105)
    - Individuals - Harnhardt-Whitney, John (Box 1, Folder 106)
    - Individuals - Jordan, Larry, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 107)
    - Individuals - Kramarsky, Werner H., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 108)
    - Individuals - Marker, Helene (Box 1, Folder 109)
    - Individuals - Moorman, Charlotte (Box 1, Folder 110)
    - Individuals - Mulder, Jan, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 111)
    - Individuals - Ochs, Hunter, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 112)
    - Individuals - Oliveros, Pauline, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 113)
    - Individuals - Paik, Nam June, 1980-2006 (Box 1, Folder 114)
    - Individuals - Pickover, Clifford A. (Box 1, Folder 115)
    - Individuals - Popper, Frank, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 116)
    - Individuals - Redmond, Catherine, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 117)
    - Individuals - Reiser, Beverly, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 118)
    - Individuals - Sender, Ramon, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 119)
    - Individuals - Subotnick, Joan La Barbara (Box 1, Folder 120)
    - Individuals - Tenney, James, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 121)
    - Individuals - Tudor, David, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 122)
    - Individuals - Vitiello, Stephen, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 123)
    - Individuals - Westermann, Joanna Beall (Box 1, Folder 124)
    - Individuals - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 125)
    - Institutions - American Poetry Review, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 126)
    - Institutions - Art in America, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 127)
    - Institutions - The Art Students League of New York, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 128)
    - Institutions - Baltimore Film Forum, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 129)
    - Institutions - The Butler Institute of American Art, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 130)
    - Institutions - Dia Art Foundation, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 131)
    - Institutions - Duke University, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 132)
    - Institutions - European American Music Distributors Corporation, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 133)
    - Institutions - Everson Museum, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 134)
    - Institutions - Eyebeam Atelier, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 135)
    - Institutions - The Franklin Institute, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 136)
    - Institutions - Guggenheim Museum SoHo, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 137)
    - Institutions - The Institute for Art and Urban Resources, Inc., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 138)
    - Institutions - Joseloff Gallery, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 139)
    - Institutions - Kingsborough Community College Art Gallery of the City University of New York, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 140)
    - Institutions - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 141)
    - Institutions - Mills College, 1996-2004 (Box 1, Folder 142)
    - Institutions - Mt. Utsayantha Regional Arts League, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 143)
    - Institutions - Musee d'Art Moderne de la Ville de Paris, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 144)
    - Institutions - Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles, CA, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 145)
    - Institutions - Museum of Modern Art, Brooklyn, NY, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 146)
    - Institutions - National Council on the Arts, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 147)
    - Institutions - New Museum of Contemporary Art, Brooklyn, NY, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 148)
    - Institutions - The New York Times, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 149)
    - Institutions - Oregon College of Education, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 150)
    - Institutions - The Painting Center, New York, NY, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 151)
    - Institutions - Pilgrim Society, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 152)
    - Institutions - PSC-CUNY Research Award Program, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 153)
    - Institutions - Rennaissance Center, Detroit, MI, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 154)
    - Institutions - San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 155)
    - Institutions - Santa Barbara Museum of Art, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 156)
    - Institutions - Scott Alan Fine Arts Gallery, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 157)
    - Institutions - Seoul Film Festival, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 158)
    - Institutions - Simon Gallery, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 159)
    - Institutions - Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 160)
    - Institutions - Stedelijk Museum Amsterdam, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 161)
    - Institutions - Studio 18 Gallery, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 162)
    - Institutions - Tibor de Nagy Gallery, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 163)
    - Institutions - The University of Iowa, Center for the New Performing Arts, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 164)
    - Institutions - Walter Wickiser Gallery, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 165)
    - Institutions - Washburn Gallery, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 166)
    - Institutions - Westdeutscher Rundfunk WDR, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 167)
    - Institutions - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1967-1993 (Box 1, Folder 168)
    - Institutions - The Woody Guthrie Film Project, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 169)
    - Institutions - Ylem, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 170)
- Series II: Book Collection, Martin, Tony, 1937 -
  Scope and Content note
  The book collection is housed in the Fales Library. The books have been catalogued in Bobcat. A keyword or related name search with the name "Tony Martin" will retrieve the records - see "Separated Materials" for a list of the removed books.
  Wise, Howard
- Series III: Media
  Conditions Governing Access
  Researcher access is limited to subseries A and C - Access Copies. There may not be access material available for all original material. Please see a Fales archivist for access.
  - Subseries A: Video Recordings - Access Copies
    - "Bridge", 1980 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0023)
      Format: DVD
      TRT: 00:22:00
    - "Flash" performance - Katonah Museum of Art - 2/7/81, 1981 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0024)
      TRT: 00:43:00
    - Morton Subotnick Volume 2: Electronic Works - Sidewinder (with liquid light show by Tony Martin) & Until Spring, 2004 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0013)
      TRT: [00:57:18]
    - Who You Are Looking For Is Who Is Looking, 1992 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0030)
      General Note
      TRT: [00:06:00]
    - Tape Music Center Concert Retrospective, [n.d.] (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0032)
      TRT: [01:42:00]
    - SF Tape Music Center Revisited, Undated (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0034)
      TRT: [01:20:00]
    - Five Stanzas, 2003 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0036)
      TRT: [00:14:00]
    - Over Under Across, 2003 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0038)
      TRT: [00:09:00]
    - Five Stanzas: Tony Martin Painting-In-Time (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0040)
      TRT: [00:05:00]
    - Tony Martin Interview: January 28, 2004 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0043)
      TRT: [00:37:00]
    - Conversing/Ear to the Ground/In the Wake of Edges, 2005 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0046)
      TRT: [00:15:00]
    - Sunloom, 2005 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0049)
      TRT: [00:07:00]
    - Wow and Flutter: The San Francisco Tape Music Center 1961-Now (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0051)
      TRT: [01:16:00]
    - "Play I" - Tony Martin, Undated (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0054)
      TRT: [00:03:00]
    - Tony Martin - Improvisations, 10/13/2004 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0057)
      TRT: [00:27:00]
    - Light Marks Converse, 2004 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0060)
      TRT: [01:03:00]
    - Game Room at Howard Wise Gallery, 1968 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0062)
      TRT: [00:02:00]
    - Tony Martin Interview, Feb. 27, 2004 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0065)
      TRT: [02:00:00]
      Program content: Made by Cort Worthington for Eyebeam. First hour, Tony Martin talks about his developement as an artist and his artistic philosphy; his aesthetic issues and concerns; and his use of material tools (multimedia, new media, painting). The second hour, Martin discusses the development processes of Eyebeam, his work with this process, and his views on direction.
    - Tony Martin Interview with Julie Martin, Feb. 7, 2007 (Media Shelf, Media ID 190.0072)
      Program content: Julie Martin of Experiments in Art and Technology (E.A.T.) interviews Tony Martin. Topics explored: Martin's development using light as a medium, his visual composing, his use of analog and digital tools and processes, using optics as an art medium, and personal-custom electronics.
  - Subseries B: Video Recordings - Originals
    Consists of screen projections from Tony Martin's visual compositions, recordings of performances and an interview.
    - "Bridge", 1980 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0001)
      Format:
      TRT: [unknown]
    - "Flash" performance - Katonah Museum of Art - 2/7/81, 1981 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0002)
    - WHO YOU ARE LOOKING FOR IS WHO IS LOOKING; - Audio: STEREO - 2/18/92, 1992 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0003)
      Format: VHS
    - Tape Music Center Concert Retrospective in San Francisco, [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0004)
    - 2, [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0005)
    - FIVE STANZAS, 2003 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0006)
      Format: Betacam SP Mega
      TRT: [00:07:46]
    - Over Under Across; Finished at Standby 1/03, 2003 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0007)
      Format: Betacam SP
      TRT: [00:05:48]
    - FIVE STANZAS - silent 5 minutes - c. 1970 & 2003 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0008)
    - Tony Martin interview; Mode Records re: Brian Brandt - N.Y.C., Jan. 28 2004 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0009)
    - sunloom - 6 minutes silent, 2005 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0010)
    - Conversing; Ear to the Ground; In the Wake of Edges, 2005 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0011)
      TRT: [00:12:30]
    - Wow & Flutter: The San Francisco Tape Music Center 1961 - now, [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0012)
    - WHO YOU ARE LOOKING FOR IS WHO IS LOOKING; - Audio: STEREO - 2/18/92, 1991 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0014)
      Format: 1"
    - Light Marks Converse; ~one hour: 4 takes; 2003, 2004 - 1/27/04 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0015)
      Format: DVCam
      TRT: [01:00:00]
    - Game Room at Howard Wise Gallery, 1968 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0027)
    - Tony Martin Interview, Feb. 27, 2004 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0068)
    - "Play I"-Tony Martin, Undated (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0066)
    - Tony Martin-Improvisations, 10/13/2004 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0067)
      Format: DVD TRT: [00:27:00]
    - Tony Martin Interview with Julie Martin, Feb. 7, 2007 (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0069)
      Format: DVD TRT: [01:20:00]
    - SF Tape Music Center Revisited, Undated (Box 3, Folder ID 190.0005)
  - Subseries C: Film - Access Copies
    Scope and Content
    There are currently no film access copies available. Please see a Fales archivist.
  - Subseries D: Film - Originals
    Scope and Contents Note
    Consists of Tony Martin's visual compositions, mostly in collaboration with other artists, along with paper documentation regarding some of the works. Paper documents stored within film cans have been removed, foldered, and given the same ID number as the corresponding film element but with a letter B at end of ID number. (Ex. Film: 190.0001A, Folder 190.0001B.)
    - Tarot, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0016A)
      Format: 16mm
    - Tarot - Artist's Descriptive Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0016B)
    - Desert Ambulance; silent; 1963 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0017)
    - Room - '63-64, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0018)
    - "Play 4" Film I; all illumination for Morton Subotnick, 1967 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0019A)
    - "Play 4" Film I - Artist's Descriptive Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0019B)
    - "Play 4" Film II; all illumination for Morton Subotnick, 1967 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0020A)
    - "Play 4" Film II - Artist's Descriptive Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0020B)
- Series IV: Objects
  - Electronic Circuitry for regulating intensity and off/on of light apparatus using frequency discrete photo cells, applied in "The Well" and "Light Pendulum" (Box 5)
    Box contains folder with description of object written by Tony Martin.
- OVERSIZE: Series I: Documentary and Graphic Material
  Contains oversize documentary and graphic material. Some entries are cross-listed with entries in Series I.
  - Subseries A: Exhibitions
    - Galaxy - James Madison University, Sawhill Gallery, Harrisburg, VA ***see also*** Series I, Subseries A, Box I, Folder 40, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 171)
    - The Inaugural Show - The Painting Center, New York, NY, [n.d.] (Box 2, Folder 172)
  - Subseries B: Visual Compositions, Performances & Lectures
    - Original multi-projector light shows for groups including: The Jefferson Airplane, The Great Society, and more - Bill Graham's Fillmore West, San Francisco, CA, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 173)
    - Silver Apples of the Moon (Morton Subotnick), c1967 (Box 2, Folder 174)
    - Vector Image Wall and works on paper: Continuously changing electronic drawing (electronic system and video projection) - Institute for Art & Urban Resources, P.S. 1, Long Island City, NY ***see also*** Series I, Subseries C, Box 1, Folder 62, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 175)
    - San Francisco Tape Music Center Retrospective: Works of 1963-66 - Victoria Theater, San Francisco, CA, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 176)
  - Subseries C: Interactive Sculptures
    - Interaction Room (or Game Room) (20 x 20 x 10 room containing light and projection installation activated by viewers using game principles) - Howard Wise Gallery, New York, NY ***see also*** Series I, Subseries C, Box 1, Folder 76, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 177)
    - Press: San Francisco Bay Guardian, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 178)
  - Subseries D: Sketches, Notes & Miscellaneous
    - Sketches, Drawings for Pieces ***see also*** Series I, Subseries D, Box 1, Folder 93, [n.d.] (Box 2, Folder 179)